Adeline Herder
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Adeline Herder papers
1942-1999
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Herder, Adeline
4.3 linear feet
The papers of collage artist Adeline Herder measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1942-1999. The collection presents an overview of Herder's personal life and career as a collage artist. Her personal life is reflected through biographical material, correspondence including letters between Adeline and her husband Milton Herder, and writings and notes including appointment books. The collection offers a rich resource on Herder's artistic activity with correspondence that includes documentation of her relationship with Marjorie Jacobson and the purchase of her work by Roy Neuberger and Joseph Hirshhorn. Herder's career is further represented through exhibition files, printed material, writings and notes, and video recordings.
Provenance
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2001 by Adeline Herder.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Adeline Herder (1920-) is a collagist from New York, N.Y. and Paris.
Adeline Herder (neé Olkes) was born on August 30, 1920 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. She graduated from Olney High School, Philadelphia, in 1939. In high school, Herder supplemented her studies with summer art classes at Crouse College, Syracuse University, in 1936 and 1938. After completing high school, she enrolled in the Tyler School of Fine Art, Temple University, where she attended classes from 1939-1941. In 1941 she married Milton Herder.
Herder resumed her studies in 1945 when she enrolled at the Philadelphia Museum School. There she made the acquaintance of Roy Davis who would later represent her, first in his gallery Davis & Long Company, and then at Davis & Langdale Company. In 1950, Herder moved to New York City and enrolled in the New School for Social Research. She held her first public show of collages and constructions in 1961 at the Bodley Gallery. Herder remained in New York City until 1962.
In 1963 Herder relocated to Paris, where she resided until 1973, and continued to work on collage constructions. She also worked with the Paris Theatre Workshop and the Studio Theatre of Paris and made masks and costumes for productions including J.B. and The Skin of Our Teeth!. Herder was acquainted with other artists and writers in Paris at the time including Beauford Delaney, James Jones, and Paul Jenkins. In 1972, Joseph Hirshhorn purchased four of Herder's works, Klosters '64, Beckoning Night City, Pink Circus, and Paris (French Box) through the intermediary Marjorie Jacobson, Herder's personal friend. In 1973, Herder moved back to New York City and through Marjorie Jacobson met Joseph Hirshhorn. At this meeting Hirshhorn purchased two more of her works, Return to Paris and Gray-Green Machine. That same year, Roy Neuberger purchased three collages from Herder, First Black City, Indian Hat Trip, and Big Black City. In 1975, the works were shown in a new acquisitions exhibition at the Neuberger Museum. Herder also participated in the Color Light & Image exhibition in 1975, which was part of the United Nations celebration of International Women's Year. In 1977, Herder was awarded visiting artist status at Clayworks Studio in New York City.
Herder, under the name of Addie Herder, has been represented by many galleries including Bodley Gallery, New York City, 1961; Savage Gallery, London, 1968 to 1970; Gruenebaum Gallery, New York City, 1976 to 1980; Hokin Gallery, Palm Beach, Florida, 1981; Sid Deutsch Gallery, New York City, 1985; and Davis & Langdale Company, New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of collage artist Adeline Herder measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1942-1999. The collection presents an overview of Herder's personal life and career as a collage artist. Her personal life is reflected through biographical material, correspondence including letters between Adeline and her husband Milton Herder, and writings and notes including appointment books. The collection offers a rich resource on Herder's artistic activity with correspondence that includes documentation of her relationship with Marjorie Jacobson and the purchase of her work by Roy Neuberger and Joseph Hirshhorn. Herder's career is further represented through exhibition files, printed material, writings and notes, and video recordings.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Collagists; Collage; Women artists
Types of Materials:
Notes; Writings; Appointment books; Video Recordings
Names:
Neuberger, Roy R.; Jacobson, Marjory, 1936-; Hirshhorn, Joseph; Herder, Milton
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1944-1999 (Boxes 1, 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1942-1996 (Boxes 1, 5; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1961-1999 (Boxes 1-2, 5; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1947-1999 (Boxes 2-3, 5; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Writings and Notes, 1956-1996 (Boxes 3-4; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1950-circa 1966 (Boxes 4-5; 4 folders)
Series 7: Video Recordings, 1993, 1996 (Boxes 4-5; 5 items)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1944-1999, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 5; 0.5 linear feet)
  Biographical material includes a curriculum vitae, a list of collectors of Herder??s work, membership and political affiliation cards, passports, travel records, a grant application, and a publicity photograph of Herder with contact sheet and negatives. This series also houses a scrapbook documenting Herder??s career including awards, clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements. Much of the information in the scrapbook can also be found elsewhere in the collection, primarily in the exhibition files and printed material.
  - Curriculum Vitae and List of Collectors, 1983, 1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Financial Records and Miscellaneous Receipts, 1959, 1963, 1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Grant Application, The Pollock-Krasner Foundation, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Membership Cards and Political Affiliations, 1944, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Passports, 1955, 1959, 1963, 1968, 1973, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, Contact Sheet, and Negatives, undated (Box 1)
  - Travel File, 1955-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Award, Yetta Olkes, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1975-1999 (Box 5 (sol))
- Correspondence, 1942-1996, Series 2:; (Boxes 1, 5; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series contains the personal and professional correspondence of Adeline Herder. Included is correspondence between Addie Herder and her husband Milton, and letters from friends, family, artists, art dealers, and collectors. Correspondents include Patricia Layman Bazelon, Eugène Braun-Munk, Marina Como, Roy Davis, Sari Dienes, Dorothy Gillespie, Joseph and Olga Hirshhorn, Alice Hutchins, Marjorie Jacobson, Suzanne and Paul Jenkins, Cecily Langdale, Golda Lewis, Roy Neuberger, Victor Salvi, and Edmund Trzcinski. Also found within the papers are letters of introduction written on Herder??s behalf by Louis Wiznitzer in 1963; correspondence between Marjorie Jacobson and Herder regarding the purchase of Herder??s constructions by Roy Neuberger and Joseph Hirshhorn; a draft letter written in 1967 by Herder stating the value of a construction that was destroyed in a fire at the offices of Life Magazine; a poem written by Roy Neuberger, ??To My Friends: The Artists,?? for his seventy-fifth birthday celebration; and a photocopy of the funeral program for James Baldwin. This series also houses business and calling cards; a postcard from Juliet Man Ray; and Christmas and birthday cards from Guerney Campbell, Carmen dell??Orefice, Mary and Mike Easley, Victor Elmaleh, Suzanne and Paul Jenkins, Bob Kulicke, Ethel Lunenfeld, and Mili Dunn Weiss among others.
  Some correspondence is in French or Italian. Researchers may wish to consult the Exhibition Files series for additional correspondence.
  This series is arranged chronologically. Where dates are unknown, letters have been filed at the end of a folder or group of folders.
  - Employment Search, 1959, undated (Box 1)
  - Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden and Joseph and Olga Hirshhorn, 1972, 1976, 1993-1994, undated (Box 1)
  - Marjorie Jacobson, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters, Davis & Long Company and Davis and Langdale Company, 1978-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1942-1995, undated, (9 folders; oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 1)
  - Christmas and Birthday Cards, 1978-1996, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, undated, (Oversized items from Box 1) (Box 5 (sol))
- Exhibition Files, 1961-1999, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2, 5; 0.8 linear feet)
  Exhibition files may contain any or all of the following: correspondence; price lists; printed material including announcements, exhibition catalogs, and clippings; and photographs. Found within the files is an exhibition catalog, Roy R. Neuberger: Patron of the Arts, inscribed by Roy Neuberger.
  This series also houses a file on Beauford Delaney including correspondence, exhibition announcements, catalogs, clippings, an introduction for an exhibition catalog written by James Baldwin, and photographs of Herder at a party with Eugène Braun-Munk, Beauford Delaney, Paul Jenkins, and James Jones among others.
  Some material is in French. Researchers may also wish to consult the Correspondence series for additional exhibition materials.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Early Price List, undated (Box 1)
  - "Constructions and Collages," Bodley Gallery, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Costumes and Masks for Paris Theater, J.B. and The Skin of Our Teeth!, 1964-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Neuberger Museum and Roy Neuberger, Permanent Collection and Various Papers, 1972-1999, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 1)
  - "Color, Light, and Image," Women??s Interart Center, 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Forty Years of American Collages," Bueckner and Harpsichords, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - "Adeline Herder, Collage Constructions," Neuberger Museum, 1975-1976, undated (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collage Constructions," Gruenebaum Gallery, 1976, undated (Box 2)
  - Herder Records on Artwork, Prices and Accounts with Gruenbaum Gallery, 1976-1978, 1980, undated (Box 2)
  - "American Collage," Davis & Long Company, 1977, undated (Box 2)
  - Clayworks Studio Workshop Exhibitions, 1977-1980, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collages," Elaine Benson Gallery, 1978-1979, 1981, undated (Box 2)
  - Goddard-Riverside Community Art Show, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Guggenheim Museum, Permanent Collection, 1979-1980, 1990, 1992, undated (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collage Constructions," Davis & Long Company, 1980, undated (Box 2)
  - Saint Thomas Celebration of the Arts, Wilmington, N.C., 1982-1983, undated (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collage Constructions," Davis & Langdale Company, 1983, undated (Box 2)
  - "American 20th Century Art" and "20th Century American Art," Sid Deutsch Gallery, 1985, 1989, 1992, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Friends of L.T.D. (Louise Tolliver Deutschman)," Paris-New York-Kent Fine Art Gallery, 1987 (Box 2)
  - "The Technological Muse," Katonah Museum of Art, 1990-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collage Constructions," Davis & Langdale Company, 1993, undated (Box 2)
  - "Addie Herder, Collage-Boxes," Davis & Langdale Company, 1996, undated (Box 2)
  - Various Exhibitions, 1976-1999 (Box 2)
  - Other Artists, Beauford Delaney, 1963-1999, undated (Box 2)
  - Claywork Studio Workshop Exhibitions, 1979, undated, (Oversized items from Box 2) (Box 5 (sol))
  - Neuberger Museum and Roy Neuberger, Exhibition Catalogue and Printed Material, 1984-1999, (Oversized items from Box 1) (Box 5 (sol))
- Printed Material, 1947-1999, Series 4:; (Boxes 2-3, 5; 0.6 linear feet)
  Printed material contains announcements, invitations, exhibition catalogs for artists including Victor Elmaleh, Sonia Gechtoff, Juan Gris, Golda Lewis, Robert Rauschenberg, Mili Dunn Weiss, and clippings pertaining to Herder??s career. Also included are posters featuring Addie Herder??s constructions and a guide to Paris published circa 1967 titled Left Bank this Month.
  Some material is in French, Portuguese, or Spanish.
  - Announcements and Invitations, 1955-1995, undated, (6 folders; oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Other Artists, 1947-1989, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, Other Artists, 1990, 1991-1993 (Box 3)
  - Magazine Clippings and Offprint Articles, 1971-1999, undated (Box 3)
  - Magazines and Bulletins, circa 1967, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1988, undated, (2 folders; oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 3)
  - Monograph, The New York Review of Art, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Performance Programs and Event Participant Lists, 1982-1994, undated (Box 3)
  - Postcards and Cards, Other Artists Work, undated (Box 3)
  - Posters, undated, (Oversized items housed in Box 5) (Box 3)
  - Announcements, 1979, undated, (Oversized items from Box 2) (Box 5 (sol))
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1970, 1976-1977, 1981, undated, (Oversized items from Box 3) (Box 5 (sol))
  - Magazines and Bulletins, 1984, 1988, 1990, (Oversized items from Box 3) (Box 5 (sol))
  - Posters, undated, (Oversized items from Box 3) (Box 5 (sol))
- Writings and Notes, 1956-1996, Series 5:; (Boxes 3-4; 1.2 linear feet)
  The bulk of the material in this series consists of Herder??s appointment books which span the years 1956 through 1996. Also included are drafts of an artist statement, lecture notes, journal entries, and miscellaneous notes and notebooks. Found within the papers are index cards containing the addresses of Herder??s contacts including artists, art gallery presidents, critics, collectors, and museum curators and directors.
  - Address Books, undated (Box 3)
  - Appointment Books, 1956-1996, (16 folders) (Box 3)
  - Index Cards, Addresses, undated (Box 4)
  - Drafts of Artist Statement, 1983, undated (Box 4)
  - Lecture, ??Art Why?,?? Saint John??s Museum of Art, Wilmington, N.C., 1982-1983, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Journal Entries and Notes, 1967-1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Notes on Paints and Other Materials, undated (Box 4)
  - Notebooks, 1973, circa 1980, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
- Artwork, 1950-circa 1966, Series 6:; (Boxes 4-5; 4 folders)
  This series contains sketchbooks, miscellaneous sketches, and a self portrait in watercolor and pastel. Artwork created by other artists includes an anniversary greeting.
  - Sketchbook and Miscellaneous Sketches, circa 1960-circa 1966, undated (Box 4)
  - Artwork, Other Artists, 1950, 1955, undated (Box 4)
  - Adeline Herder Self Portrait, undated (Box 5 (sol))
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 5 (sol))
- Video Recordings, 1993, 1996, Series 7:; (Boxes 4-5; 5 items)
  This series contains a recording of a tribute to Roy Neuberger for his ninetieth birthday and includes clips of Addie Herder speaking about Roy Neuberger. This series also houses visual inventories of Herder??s works exhibited in 1993 and 1998 at Davis & Langdale Company. Also found are two ¾ inch U-Matic video recordings titled Addie Herder Collages, Tape 1, and Addie Herder Collages, Tape 2.
  - Roy Neuberger, Birthday Tribute, 1993, (1 videocassette) (Box 4)
  - Addie Herder Exhibitions at Davis & Langdale, 1993, 1996, (1 videocassette) (Box 4)
  - Addie Herder Collages, undated, (2 videocassettes) (Box 5 (sol))